Inventory of the John B. Thomas papers, 1870-1893
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
John B. Thomas papers
1870-1893
Thomas, John B.
00141
7.7 cubic feet + artifact (19 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Business records of a 19th century sheep and cattle rancher in southeast Wyoming.
Biography of John B. Thomas
Thomas had several business interests in Cheyenne, Wyoming, during the 1870s and 1880s, dealing mainly with the cattle and sheep industries. Hay & Thomas, a company formed by his partnership with Henry Gurley Hay (1847-1919), included the operation of a sheep ranch near Cheyenne, Valley Ranche. During the 1870s both Thomas and Hay served as surveyors for Wyoming Territory with the U.S. Surveyor Generals Office. Hay also operated a wholesale grocery in Cheyenne, Whipple & Hay. In 1884 Hay sold his interest in Hay & Thomas to Thomas.
Thomas also held interests in Thomas & Page, a partnership with E.A. Page; the Suffolk Cattle Company involving James B. and W.A. Crawford; Thomas & Arnett and Warner & Arnett, involving A.H. Arnett, a cattle grower in Dickinson, North Dakota, and William D. Warner of Texas; and Adams, Choate & Company in Station, Nebraska.
Scope and Content
The collection documents Thomas' cattle and sheep businesses, mainly Hay & Thomas. Hay & Thomas records include correspondence (1871-1889) including some personal letters of Thomas and of Hay and letters relating to the U.S. Surveyor Generals Office; daybooks (1873-1883); journals (1876-1888); ledgers (1870-1884); legal agreements (1871-1877); accounts with Whipple & Hay and other financial materials (1870-1892). Records of Thomas & Page (1881-1884), Suffolk Cattle Co. (1883-1893), Thomas & Arnett (1885-1890), Warner & Arnett (1884), and Adams, Choate & Co. (1888-1891) may include any of the following, letter books, cashbooks, journals, ledgers, trial balances, and legal agreements.
There are also a few materials (1873-1875) of Thomas and of Hay relating to the U.S. Surveyor Generals Office, including the field notes for his 1874 survey of the Fort Sanders military reservation outside of Laramie, Wyoming; and Thomas' records (1887-1888) on the construction of Atlas Block in Cheyenne.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by John B. Thomas at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
The collection was received from Clarence J. Dunder in 1950 and 1953.
Access Terms
United States. Surveyor General.; Whipple and Hay (Firm); Sheep ranches -- Wyoming.; Sheep industry -- Wyoming.; Surveying -- Wyoming.; Wool industry -- Wyoming.; Cattle trade -- Wyoming.; Cattle trade -- North Dakota.; Grocery trade -- Wyoming -- Cheyenne.; Cheyenne (Wyo.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Fort Sanders (Wyo.); Valley Ranche (Wyo.); Cheyenne (Wyo.) -- History.; Wyoming -- History -- to 1889.; Wyoming -- History -- 1890-1918.; Daybooks.; Journals (bookkeeping records); Ledgers.; Cashbooks.; Letterpress copybooks.; Surveyors.; Businessmen.;; Hay, Henry Gurley, 1847-1919.; Page, E. A.; Arnett, A. H.; Hay & Thomas (Firm); Thomas & Page (Firm); Suffolk Cattle Company.; Thomas & Arnett (Firm); Warner & Arnett (Firm); Adams, Choate & Company.
Agriculture and Natural Resources; Ranching; Businesses and Corporations; Wyoming
Container List
- Series I. Hay & Thomas
  - John B. Thomas and Hay & Thomas, letters received, 1871-1881 (Box 1, Folder 1-11)
  - John B. Thomas and Hay & Thomas, letters received, 1882-1888 (Box 2, Folder 1-11)
  - John B. Thomas, letters received, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - John B. Thomas and Hay & Thomas, letter books, 1876-1889 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Hay & Thomas, day books, 1873-1878 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - Hay & Thomas, day books, 1879-1883 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Hay & Thomas, journals, 1876-1888 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
  - Hay & Thomas, ledgers, 1870-1884 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Hay & Thomas, trial balance sheets, 1877, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Hay & Thomas, account books, 1876-1883 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - John B. Thomas and Hay & Thomas, bank books, 1870-1892 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Hay & Thomas, bills of purchase, 1875 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Hay & Thomas, bills of purchase, 1876-1880 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
  - Hay & Thomas, Valley Ranche, receipts, 1877-1883 (Box 6, Folder 6-9)
  - Hay & Thomas, bills and receipts, 1870-1871 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
  - Hay & Thomas, bills and receipts, 1872-1883 (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
  - John B. Thomas and Hay & Thomas, bills and receipts, 1884-1892 (Box 8, Folder 1-8)
  - Hay & Thomas, legal agreements, 1871-1877 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Series II. Thomas & Page
  - Thomas & Page, correspondence, receipts, and other records, 1881-1885 (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
  - Thomas & Page, letter book, 1881-1884 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Thomas & Page, cashbook and journal, 1881-1884 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Thomas & Page, ledger, 1881-1884 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Thomas & Page, legal agreements, 1881-1883 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Thomas & Page, transcripts (Box 19)
- Series III. Suffolk Cattle Company
  - Suffolk Cattle Company, correspondence, receipts, and other records, 1885-1893 (Box 17, Folder 5-8)
  - Suffolk Cattle Company, ledger, 1885-1886 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Suffolk Cattle Company, labor accounts, 1887-1892 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Suffolk Cattle Company, miscellaneous financial, 1883-1884 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Suffolk Cattle Company, legal agreements, 1888-1893 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Suffolk Cattle Company, transcripts (Box 19)
- Series IV. Thomas & Arnett
  - Thomas & Arnett, correspondence, receipts, and other records, 1886-1890 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Thomas & Arnett, trial balances, 1885-1890 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Thomas & Arnett, legal agreements, 1885-1890 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Series V. Warner & Arnett
  - Warner & Arnett, ledger, 1884 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Warner & Arnett, legal agreements, 1884 (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Series VI. Adams, Choate & Company
  - Adams, Choate & Company, letter book, 1888 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Adams, Choate & Company, letters received, 1888-1890 (Box 11, Folder 2-4)
  - Adams, Choate & Company, daybook, 1888 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Adams, Choate & Company, legal agreements, 1888-1891 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Thomas B. Adams, notary seal, undated (Box 18)
- Series VII. John B. Thomas
  - Correspondence of A.H. Arnett, 1880-1884 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Property log book, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Horse record, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - U.S. Deputy Surveyor materials, 1873-1875 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - U.S. Deputy Surveyor materials, Fort Sanders survey, 1874 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Atlas Block, Cheyenne, construction, 1887-1888 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous materials, 1876-1891 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
- Series VIII. Henry G. Hay
  - U.S. Deputy Surveyor materials, 1873-1874 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - U.S. Deputy Surveyor materials, Fort Bridger survey, 1874 (Box 17, Folder 12)
- Series IX. General
  - Cancelled checks, 1870-1891 (Box 13-15)
  - stenographer's notebooks, blank stock certificates and checks, undated (Box 16)
  - U.S. Deputy Surveyor materials, Fort Laramie survey, 1873 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence of George Haywood, 1887, 1896 (Box 17, Folder 14)